So those are the sorts of like really
core skills. Do we teach that in school?
Is that something that you can go to
university and this is what makes this
shift so interesting that a lot of the
skills that appear to be becoming very
critical are things that you mature into
and that's where my conundrum is. How do
you teach those? How do you short
circuit that that experience-based
deliberate practice learning process?
First of all, if AI is producing the
code and we review it, what's the fun in
that Annie?
Yeah, that's a really great question and
you're right. We don't make great
reviewers. You're listening to the AI
Native Dev brought to you by
[Music]
Tessle. Hello and welcome to another
episode of the AI Native Dev. Joining me
today is Annie Vela. And Annie is a
distinguished engineer at Westpak in New
Zealand. And I loved a story that Annie
and I just just shared when off air
whereby it was 6 years old Annie was
when she built her first computer which
was a Commodore 64 which was wonderful
and that really kicked Annie off into
the engineering world. and he's got a
very large engineering background from
an half IC half engineering leadership
and actually also doing a part-time
masters exploring the impact of AI
coding assistance in software
engineering at the University of Aland
massive welcome to the AI native dev.
How are you? Thank you very much Simon.
I'm great and I'm very glad to be here
speaking with you today. And you're in
New Zealand, so it was a little bit
tricky. A little bit tricky finding time
for the recording, but we'll let the
viewers work out whether it's AM or PM.
Your side and my side, but we're at 12
hours. Exactly. 12, sorry, 11 hours, I
think, apart. Yes. Yeah. Every time I
try and schedule something with somebody
overseas, it's a matter of using any
tool possible to work out that time
difference. It's quite Absolutely. Oh
gosh, time zones are hard. So, we're
talking today actually because of a
wonderful blog piece that you wrote and
it I think it's one of those things that
will absolutely resonate with our
audience. Your blog is titled the
software engineering identity crisis and
from our point of view we're thinking a
lot of the similar kind of concepts of
how our roles and software engineering
in general will change with the
introduction of AI coding assistance and
becoming more of a driver in the world
of software engineering. Why don't we
start perhaps tell us a little bit about
the blog the summary of the blog the
highle view of what you covered. Sure. I
guess it it starts with the fact that I
have, like you mentioned, been a
software engineer in one way, shape or
form for a very long time. And I've
absolutely loved it. I've loved being a
coder. I've loved being a problem
solver. And you know, with this
introduction of this new amazing
technology, which it just feels like
magic, one can't help but wonder, okay,
what is that going to do to the
day-to-day job of a software engineer?
And it's exactly the same reason why I
chose to do that as a mast's topic. But
I've been digging deep into really
what's driving me to ask these
questions, right? Is it because I want
to help design better AI tools for
people to use? Or is it because I guess
deep down inside I fear that we might be
losing something, the thing that
attracted me and many others to becoming
a software engineer in the first place.
And I've been writing a bit about the
journey and learning how to use these
tools. And I've been using wind surf.
That's probably my go-to at the moment
aside from chat GBT. But for coding,
Windsurf, I find it incredible. I've
written a bit about that. But I really
hadn't gotten to the root of what I
guess what I think about a lot, what I
like talking about, what I'm trying to
really get to the bottom of as part of
my masters. And it came down to there's
a lot of productivity gains to be made
with these tools. is yes our roles are
changing but at the core of it we're
losing something as well and a lot of us
software engineers we've tied our
identity to the work that we do we're
very proud of the code that we write of
the solutions we come up with and that
very much depends on what stage of your
career you might be at but certainly in
those formative years when you're
learning how to code how to structure
your code how to find the bug how to fix
it you're
actually refining those skills through
practice
And if now we're delegating those to to
an AI, to a tool, then you're not going
to get to practice those things anymore.
And so you're not going to be
necessarily forming those skills, but
you might also not be doing the thing
that that you enjoy doing the most. I
reflect on on my years as an IC and also
all the time that I've spent coding in
my spare time because we also do that,
right? That moment when you get into the
zone and we sometimes we call it flow
state. We might refer to it in different
ways, but it's that moment when you know
what it is that needs to be done. You've
solved the problem in your head to some
degree. At least you have a path. Maybe
you got some good music on. I know for
me it was always like in these big
headphones with good fun music playing
that that sort of drowned out the rest
of the world. And then it felt to me
like I was playing the piano. Like I
when I was writing code in that mode, I
the world disappeared and it was just me
and the computer and I was making the
magic happen through my own skills,
ability to type fast because I learned
my I taught myself to to type quickly
when I was pretty young. And all of that
almost doesn't matter anymore. You might
not get to do that as much anymore. You
might there's no one preventing you from
doing that. But certainly in the
workplace, if you can just get an AI to
generate at least all the boilerplate
code for you much much faster, why why
wouldn't you? Why would your employer
say, "Yeah, no, no worries. Just type it
out slowly. It's okay. We prefer No,
it's for sure that Pandora's box has
been opened. The genie's out of the
bottle. These tools are here. They're
here to stay and they are magical, but
they replace a part of us that I think a
lot of us quite enjoy doing." So diving
into that, I started thinking more about
so what does that really mean though? So
fine, perhaps we're letting go of
something that meant something that we
we tied ourselves up with. But by the
same token, some of us have already
experienced changes like that in our
careers. And upon reflection, I have by
becoming a manager partway through my
career very reluctantly because I really
enjoyed the coding and I didn't want to
move away from it. I thought, is there a
parallel I could draw there? And the
more I thought about it, the more
actually maybe that's the angle to lean
into to realize that you don't need to
choose one or the other. There is the
engineer manager pendulum that charity
majors talks about. So maybe here
there's something similar that we can
swing between the two sides. It doesn't
have to be one or the other. Finding the
balance might be the right approach for
many of us at least. And yeah, so all of
that resulted in a very long blog post
to be honest. It's a lengthy one, but I
clearly had a lot to say. Yeah. And it's
been very well shared. And I guess that
that experience that you had, I guess,
with moving from an engineer to a
manager clearly brought back some
memories there from when when you
started using Windsurf or other tools.
It brought back memories from I guess
when you did move from engineering to a
management role. May maybe there's
others actually listeners who have done
that similar move and stepped away from
the day-to-day coding much more. I guess
that was presumably your inspiration,
your motivation for building the post.
What when you move from an engineer to a
manager, I guess you when you manage a
team, it's slightly different. Perhaps
you're even further away, maybe more
managing a project versus having more of
that creative aspect. I think there are
going to be I guess there's probably two
different styles of roles there in the
management of engineering teams. One is
probably more hands-on, one is one is
more kind of like maybe the project
management. So there's probably people
who are more hands-on and more
hands-off. From the development side
when you're now using AI
tools, how much enjoyment do you feel
you
lose moving more to a promptbased way of
developing? Do you have that real
connection to writing code or do you
still feel like there's a level of
creativity, a level of feedback that
still provides you with that need that
you know that that thing that we desire
in terms of actually being able to
create, build and achieve something
through through building code. Yeah,
certainly think that there's still an
element of creativity like it it's
probably more in the eye of the
beholder, right? So it it depends on
what it is that you personally as an
individual enjoy out of building
solutions. I'm a problem solver. I enjoy
doing puzzles of any sort. So for me
using these tools, there's a real
positive aspect which is I get to see a
result much quicker because let's face
it, this sort of stuff that I'm using it
for in my own home projects and helping
me analyze some of the data that I'm
collecting as part of my masters, time
is of essence and the quicker I can get
something up and running, the better for
me. the sooner I get the insights and
stuff. But if I think about the switch
from becoming from being a software
engineer to moving into management now,
I don't know if I'm unique in in this
way, but there was a time when I wasn't
even that far into my career. I want to
say maybe five or six years into my
career thinking of a career as like a 40
year long thing. Five years isn't long,
right? And already I had people saying,
"You might like to consider a move into
management because you've got some
really great soft skills and I think
you'd make a great manager." And I just,
"No, this is not why I became a software
engineer. I like building code. I like
working directly with the computer and
like solving the problem myself. Having
that sense of accomplishment, that
satisfaction of seeing something build
and then working out that actually
there's a better way I can do it." It's
a very personal thing that you're doing
one-on-one with the computer, right? I
didn't want to give that up, not so
early in my career. And and I had a bit
of pressure from various managers to
consider a move into management. And I
kept it at bay until about 10 years into
my career when I finally realized that I
had reached a point where I wasn't
really learning all that much more about
how to write better code. It writing the
code didn't seem that hard anymore. I
could do it. I knew I could do it. I was
teaching myself other skills like how to
debug memory leaks and just trying to
get into s something slightly deeper,
something slightly more complex. So
eventually I succame to the idea that
okay fine, I will try being a manager
because there's no doubt some skills
that I might be able to learn there. But
then that transition is quite hard. And
I don't think many companies recognize
that taking someone who was a pretty
good software engineer and then moving
them into management, it's not always a
smooth transition. And it's something
that I talk with a lot of people when
I'm interviewing for other managers. If
this is their first fora into
management, I always ask them why. What
is it that's pushing you towards this?
And you know, there's always a variety
of answers, but I make sure that they
understand that in in a management role,
you're going to have different
priorities and you're going to spend
your time on different things. So, if
the job description implies that you
might still get to code 50% of the time,
that's unlikely to happen. As much as
you might want it to happen, managing
people or projects or, you know,
anything that's more wet wear is is a
whole different ballgame. It's a
different set of skills. You're leaning
into communication skills into a bit of
empathy about understanding the
relationships between people, the
strengths and weaknesses and how you
pair up people so that you create
opportunities for people to to learn and
do their best work. So, you're really
learning quite a different skill set
that you're practicing daytoday. And
this is the identity crisis that you
mentioned because you say in the blog
that we find our identity in building
things not managing things. And I think
from the move from an engineer to a
manager very often somewhat hopefully at
least somewhat it's the individual's
choice to to move into management. So
there's almost they're trying to fulfill
the decision that they've made. with if
we draw a parallel to some of the AI
tools and engineers using AI tools
today, there are going to be people who
are having AI tools forced upon them by
it's amazing. We're seeing a number of
companies now that that are almost like
saying yes, we absolutely want you to
use this and if you're not, you need to
be telling us why you're not using these
productivity tools essentially. What can
we learn from from folks like yourself
who have moved from an engineer to a
manager role? How do we best at least as
we go through this identity crisis again
moving into an AI native world or or a
software development world with AI
tools? How do we best either embrace
this identity crisis or at least manage
it in some way whereby we can still
succeed even if we do or don't embrace
some of the concepts of AI and software
engineering. Yeah, you're absolutely
right. I was thinking about this earlier
today as well just that as a software
engineer moving into management
theoretically that's a choice whereas
here perhaps won't have a choice really
I think what's important is to probably
not resist it because as you say at
sooner or later you're probably going to
be in a job where you're expected to use
these tools and learn to use them really
well because they're your new toolkit.
embrace the change because ultimately
what it's doing is allowing you to build
a new set of skills. And some of us get
to the that point in our career where we
recognize I did that by staying in the
same role that I'd been in for a while,
I wasn't really gaining a whole lot of
new skills. So maybe it was the right
time for me to accept a a sideways move
into a management role where essentially
I I felt like I went back to being a
novice and I was learning how to do
one-on- ones, how to set up a hiring
process and an interview process and how
to do performance reviews and all of
that which was so different. I did not
go to university and learn all of that
stuff like I did the programming that I
was taught. But by doing those those
jobs and setting all of that up and
caring deeply about it, I learned a
whole lot of new skills that that have
come quite handy even when I've returned
to IC roles. Just being able to see the
world through the lens of what would my
manager think about this or why is my
manager asking me to do this thing that
feels to me like it makes no sense. But
actually having been in their shoes now,
I can understand better the perspective
that they have. So you do learn so many
new skills. So just accept that it
there's an
opportunity to see it through that lens
and build up a whole new set of skills
around how to not just how to
communicate better because I think
that's one of the fundamental skills of
getting good with these tools, but also
a whole bunch of new jobs are going to
crop up. The term AI engineer is now
floating around. There's going to need
to be things built around prompt
libraries and specifications, how to
write specs really well or how to verify
that the AI is outputting the right code
or that making the right decisions.
We're now working with non-determinism,
which is something that probably makes a
lot of us quite uncomfortable. So, how
do we manage that? How do we accept that
there's likely to be a lot of
unpredictability in in both using them
as AI coding assistants but also if
we're building agentic systems. So
suddenly there's there will be new areas
of specialization that you can gravitate
towards. So it's not like the doors
closing. It's just shifting and and a
whole new set of skills will become
apparent as really important into the
future. So I guess it's being open to
that change. Yeah. And I think there's a
couple of things there actually. One
thing that you mentioned there is being
accepting of that and being like almost
very openly wanting to learn those new
skills is super important. I think we'll
be faced with folks who are just coming
into the industry who are ramping up on
these skills so fast almost like it's
the way versus a change. And there are
individuals on the in the industry who
have been in the industry for many years
who are going to be at a disadvantage
somewhat because people are jumping into
this AI space so fast. However, those
people have a massive advantage in
understanding and knowing how software
is built from the ground up. And we were
talking about this off air and you
mentioned about going through that
experience of there's a there's an issue
in prod we need to understand why we
need to learn the lessons essentially of
everything from bad code to bad design,
bad architectures as to why these things
happen. And so it's we're in a people
who are in the industry now have that
unique that that unique knowledge of I
guess that mechanical sympathy of how
things work under the covers as well as
the opportunity to learn about learn
about the new AI technologies on top and
that's going to probably be fairly
unique somewhat in many years to come
having that in-depth knowledge. Yeah.
And I guess there are parallels in
history like I mentioned the industrial
revolution which obviously I wasn't
around for. History repeats itself. So I
think there are instances like like the
one that I mentioned but also I wasn't
around when the when compilers were
introduced. But I imagine that the
generation of engineers that were
halfway through their careers when that
shift happened, they also had to learn
to trust this thing that was now
outputting the code that they previously
had to write by hand and understand
intimately. There would have been, I'm
sure, lots of criticism on the compiler
cannot possibly create assembler as as
good as I can and all of that or how am
I going to know how to debug it because
I didn't write it. There are lessons we
can look back on and see how did they
work through that shift and how were
they either at an advantage or a
disadvantage and what can we do to help
those that will find it more challenging
for a variety of reasons. Actually on
that topic I came across a very long 290
page World Economic Forum on skills and
the job market looking forward to 2030.
Seems like a long way away. It's really
not but it's a huge document. So clearly
I have not read it all but what caught
my attention was this sort of quadrants
on what skills will become more
important or less important and the one
that sort of stands out is the most
important well it's currently already
important and it will become more
important was resilience flexibility and
agility. So those are the sorts of like
really core skills. Do we teach that in
schools? Is that something that you can
go to university and stud? This is what
makes this shift so interesting that a
lot of the skills that appear to be
becoming very critical are things that
you mature into. And that's where my
conundrum is. How do you teach those?
How do you short circuit that that
experience-based deliberate practice
learning process and moonshoot right to
you're already critically thinking, you
are thinking at a higher level. you have
this holistic perspective like that's
the right hand side of the Drafus model
where you've reached a level of expert
and you're functioning from a level of
intuition. How do you build intuition if
you haven't lived through it? So yeah,
that's the big question mark for me.
Yeah, very interesting. In in the blog
you talk about shifting roles which is
obviously a big part of the post and you
mentioned going from effectively
builders to managers from creators to
orchestrators instead of writing code to
managing AI systems. You referenced
actually Patrick Dwis who wrote who
wrote the the four patterns of AI native
development which is still something
that is very much up for community
involvement and contributions. Patrick
talks about going from implementation to
intent, from producer to manager, which
is obviously very aligned with your
post, from delivery to discovery, and
from content to knowledge. We'll link
both of these posts in the show notes as
well. But in in producer to manager,
which I think is most relevant here,
Patrick talks about the fact that first
of all, in fact, there's a few things
here that are probably quite relevant.
He talks about AI produces the code, you
review the code. And I think that's a
problem. You know, we're not good at
reviewing other people's code anyway.
So, this is going to be, we'll talk
about this a little bit in terms of how
much of a skill we need to really build
there. I guess funwise, creativity wise,
how interesting that's going to be.
Patrick also talks about the cognitive
load reduction, which is interesting.
talking about how AI can effectively
give us contextual annotations and
explain much much more uh of what code
changes are happening versus perhaps a
diff with red and green highlights.
Acceptance fatigue which is a big
problem and I think this happens a lot
with code review but will very much
likely happen. I do it a lot more than I
wish to admit with cursor and things
like that where some it worked the first
few times. Let's just keep accepting it
and trusting whether it does that. Is
that a good thing as things become
reliable enough? And of course the
situational and aware awareness
effectively when something fails can AI
help us with that because if we didn't
write that code it's hard for us to be
able to identify where something went
wrong. So yeah, you cover this very
lovely, very beautifully in your blog as
well with creators from writing code to
orchestrators which is effectively
managing those AI systems and you talk a
little bit about reclaiming
responsibilities doing more design work
and systems thinking and things like
that which today is a very specialist
area and people specific people do that.
So I guess let's take that a little bit
from the top down. I've mentioned a few
things there. First of all, if AI is
producing the code and we review it,
what's the fun in that, Annie?
Yeah, that's a really great question and
you're right. We don't make great
reviewers. I know as a software engineer
or even as a manager of software
engineers begging people to please
review your code. You've got this PR.
You'd really like to get it merged in,
but it's a bit long. And I'm sorry about
that. I went overboard with the
refactoring. It's hard enough to do that
when you've written all the code
yourself, so there isn't discreets of
it. How do we make it fun? Whoever
solves that problem will probably be
quite a rich
person. So, I love the ideas that that
Patrick writes about with the the better
than just the green and red diffs.
You're thinking back to the days when we
didn't even have great diff tools. Like
just I think that the trick with using
these tools and it's something that I
mentioned to people who are just
starting to play with it is source
control is your friend like frequent
commits frequent PRs because it can just
get away from you. It sounds like you've
experienced that a bit yourself like it
before you know it you've changed 18
files in ways that you didn't expect to
and now it's becoming a bit overwhelming
even for yourself to know which ones to
pick for your PR. That's not a great
state to be in because you're you're
going to end up committing stuff that
well where if you're honest with
yourself, you probably haven't really
checked and then the next person in line
who reviews your code may not really
check either because vigilance fatigue
is a thing. And yeah, that that's going
to become a bigger problem I imagine.
And I think that the 2024 DORA report
already starts to point at that. They've
shown that for all of the productivity
gains and even the increase in code
quality, we are seeing a slight decrease
in that delivery stability and that
potentially attributed to the fact that
PRs are getting bigger. people are just
accepting code that may have more issues
in it and therefore there's a bit more
code churn where we're seeing an
increase in the a more recent get clear
report that I mentioned in my blog post
showed some pretty staggering figures on
code duplication and increases in code
duplication increases in that code churn
code that's released and then has to be
quickly modified and re-released likely
because it had a problem in it so yeah I
think we're going to the Dora report
will be an interesting thing to keep an
eye on over the next few years as we go
much faster, but are we more productive
if we're actually just rolling back code
more often and having to redo the same
bit of work and like probably producing
a lot more code, but maybe not in the
ways that we thought we would gain the
productivity. We're gaining productivity
here and then losing it here. You're
just shifting your focus. Yeah. And I
think over time as well, over time we're
going to be if we're stepping away from
code that much, are we the right people
to actually decide what good code looks
like or do we actually need to have much
more of a reliance on testing and
autonomy to be able to say irrespective
of how good this code is, it is doing
the right thing or it's not doing the
right thing. And yes, we can do things
to to make things more performant and so
forth or maybe refactor it to be more
maintainable, better looking code, but
we know it's doing the right thing or we
know it's doing the wrong thing. And I
feel sometimes actually the review
almost needs to be more
focused potentially around the
correctness versus the style which I
think a lot of reviews typically over
rotate on. So yeah, I wonder how much of
that can be automated out through much
better testing, which we I guess
historically have never been great at,
but we need to rely much more upon it
because that's probably far more
interesting than actually sitting
through looking at code reviews. When I
do code reviews, not I don't do code
reviews in the sense that I am the only
person reviewing code, but I still read
through code because one, I find it
interesting, and two, it's the closest
I'm going to get to the truth. Like when
somebody says, "Oh, we solved the
problem." rather than asking them to
describe it to me if they're busy, I
could probably just go look at the code.
And over the years, you get you get
pretty good at recognizing the shape of
code. I like to that's what I like to
refer it as. If I see it on a page, as
long as it's relatively well structured
code, you can pretty quickly recognize
the flow. And and I guess that's maybe a
skill that we will need to build into
one another. How do you get good at
recognizing which parts of the code you
should spend more time reviewing for
that element of correctness that you
very rightly pointed out? Because
testing is automated testing.
Absolutely. Verification. Today I came
across a blog post that talked about
product managers now starting to focus
on this idea of building evals
as a sort of analogy to unit testing
which was for more deterministic
systems. product managers who are
perhaps looking to
build very cool agentic systems that can
book a flight to wherever you ask it to
on your behalf. Please find me a great
weekend getaway somewhere around San
Francisco and off it goes except half
the time you end up with a flight booked
to middle of nowhere and that's not what
you asked for. So how do you prevent
that from happening? they're starting to
come up much like we've started to talk
about specdriven development and stuff.
Product managers are talking about this
concept of evals and that's evaluating
that the output was in line with what
they expected it to be. And I don't know
what sort of tools they're imagining,
but you start to see the importance of
that safety net, the guard rail that you
know, the more automation you can put
around that, the better because
otherwise we're all just going to become
AI babysitters is watching its output
and preventing the things to leak in
ways that we don't want them to. And I'm
not sure that there's as much joyfulness
in that type of work as there is in
being the creator. Yeah. Yeah. No, I I
completely agree. I completely agree.
When we think about when we think about
skills that developers are going to need
to be successful and to be that creator,
we talked about some of the kind of the
flexibility, the ability to change,
those types of things. From a skills
point of view that is more more specific
to to development, whether it's things
like I guess prompt engineering and
things like that, what do you feel are
things that are going to probably be
hardest to let go of from a development
point of view? And perhaps there's some
analogy here to I guess moving from
engineering to management. And once we
move away from them or dep prioritize
those, what do you feel the most
important skills that we need to grow to
be successful as an AI assisted
developer or an AI native developer?
What that makes me think of is I don't
know when the last time you sat an
interview for a software engineering
role yourself, Simon, but we still tend
to ask a lot of very very detailed
questions. So, I'll tell you a little
story. I interviewed for a job at Google
when I was about 3 years into my career.
It was my absolute dream to work for
Google and it this was before the days
of video conferencing. So, it was
literally over the phone. I had to hold
a telephone up to my and try and solve
some very interesting puzzle brain
teaser questions. I guess it was just
before the days of elite code, right?
Needless to say, I didn't pass that
interview. Eventually, I was offered the
job, but it was not in the domain that I
want that was a software engineer in
test and I had an issue with that and
that's for another blog.
Throughout the years, I've noticed that
we still quiz software engineers on
their ability to solve these sorting
algorithms or search algorithms or like
recursion. Can you reverse a linked
list? Like the industry still believes
and maybe it's changing now, but we have
until now still believed that those
skills are absolutely critical to you
being employed as a very skilled
software engineer. And then I'd say 90%
of the time you join the company and you
don't get to work on things like that.
You're you are stitching together
libraries that someone else has written
the fancy sorting algorithm for. Why on
earth would you go and write your own
unless you work for Google and you're
probably not going to be building the
next fancy sorting algorithm from
scratch. And it means that there are
literally people who enjoy going through
those sorts of elite coding exercises on
there's a reason that website exists,
right? There's leaderboards of people
who can solve the most complex problems
the fastest. So that I don't think will
be very important anymore. That's a
skill that a lot of software engineers
have taken to be the core of being a
really strong software engineer. That is
a skill I think we're going to need to
learn to let go of both in interviews
and personally. It just it won't make
much sense anymore. Why would you need
to be an expert at writing that level of
code when an AI can probably generate
something good enough for you? That
alone leaves a big gap because when I
think of that, I think of a really even
today like I'm not close to product
code, let's say today. But I think of
those kind of things as it's
challenging. They're problem solving.
They're interesting problems to solve.
Do we have a replacement for that or do
we need to learn to love other
challenges? I think it it's you're going
up a level like in terms of a level of
abstraction perhaps. I think it's still
very important to understand how systems
work, how they interact, what where your
interfaces are and how to make sure that
you protect parts of the system from
from a resilience perspective, S sur.
These concepts are still important, but
do they give you that dopamine hit that
you get when you finally get that
recursion to work the way that you want
it to? I'm not convinced it's the same.
So, I don't know exactly what you would
replace it with. Maybe for fun, you
might still go and do some of that type
of work, but it's that's going to
diminish. It can't possibly not. I
suppose they just there might still be
some people that enjoy writing a bit of
assembly just because it's something
that they enjoyed doing a few years ago,
but it's not something that you probably
need to do for an interview or in your
day-to-day job anymore. So, that's what
I mean. I guess this is where the
identity crisis blog post why it meant
so much to me because I there are some
gaps there that I can't square up. I
can't see precisely how we're going to
get quite the same type of enjoyment out
of this type of role. But certainly
knowing for the next for the foreseeable
future there is still going to be plenty
of work in understanding systems knowing
how to hand code or hand change code
because we software is everywhere. It's
embedded into everything. And we all
know that there are still older systems
that run on very old technology, old
programming languages. There are still
plenty of Cobalt developers out there
who are gainfully employed. And I'm sure
that 30 years ago, someone was probably
thinking that was a timelmited offer.
And yet, here we are in 2025, and I'm
good friends with a few. So, I know that
things will change. Some things will
change much quicker and some people will
move with that change quickly and others
will take their time and perhaps really
find a niche for themselves and being
able to leverage those skills. But yeah,
this is what makes this entire topic so
fascinating and so quickly evolving.
Yeah, we're talking about today may not
be valid in a week's time. Yeah, very
true. Very true. Incidentally, those
developers are very well paid as well.
those. Yeah, maybe we've got something
to look forward to. There we go. There
we go. So, you mentioned systems
thinking those that like when we think
about that level of abstraction, we're
thinking more about the architecture,
more about the systems, more about the
interconnectivity between those apps.
Are those going to be more of the skills
I guess from an application point of
view that we need to that we need to
either either grow or recognize we need
to spend more effort in because I think
those are some of the parts that
actually make the
applications you know that much better
because it's it has a greater impact in
very often with how they actually work
and how they run and how they work with
each other and how they're maintainable.
Yeah. How successful they are in the
end. Right. they even solve the customer
problem that you were trying to solve.
That's where I think the other part of
that blog post and another one that I've
written as well comes into play.
Something I noticed during my career and
I suspect there's many factors at play
here but when I went to university and
did my compsside degree I was taught the
whole software development life cycle
from eliciting requirements by
interviewing customers understanding
what the problem they were trying to
solve was trying to steer them away from
telling me what this what they thought
the solution should be working through
use cases at the time UML was still
quite popular so modeling it all using
UML and working through some scenarios
for each of those use cases and then
thinking about all of the the testing
that would need to be done, the
different types of testing, all the edge
cases and then building it and applying
all the testing thinking and then
maintaining it and upgrading it and all
of that. So the full end to end I was
lucky enough to do all of those things
and a number of the jobs I've had and
part of it might be that I've also a lot
of the jobs I've had have been at
smaller companies either startups like
quite small startups 10 people even less
in some cases up to scaleups with 400ish
people and in those sorts of
organizations you tend to wear a lot of
hats whatever needs doing if you've got
either the skills to do it or the
interest or there's no one else. So
you're you end up exercising those
skills and practicing them and learning
as you go and you build up this holistic
picture of what it takes to build a
system like this. Yeah. But throughout
the years, what at least I feel like
I've noticed is this huge demand for
software engineering because like I said
before, software just runs the world
now, doesn't it? Imagine a world where
you don't have a mobile phone in your
pocket with constant internet and all
the apps that you rely on today, the
games you play and the media that you
spend too much time scrolling through.
Imagine a world without that. It's
really hard to imagine, but software
runs all of that. So behind the scenes,
there are all these software engineers
busily building up all of these systems
that we just take for granted today,
right? So that has meant a huge increase
in demand for the ability to build
software. And no matter how hard
universities tried, they still weren't
pumping out enough graduates who could
do the job. So I I think what ended up
happening is we recognized as an ind
industry that we needed to apply a bit
of specialization here. So of those who
went through the the appropriate level
of education, whatever that means in the
context of the individual, you now get
to focus on coding because no one else
can do that bit. You should do the
coding. We're going to get someone else
to design it. We'll give that to an
architect and we're going to get someone
else to understand what the problem was.
That's a product owner or a product
manager. We're going to get someone else
to test it for you. So, you don't have
to waste your time on that. It's someone
else's job. We'll get operations.
They're going to deploy it for you and
run it. They'll be on call. So, don't
worry about it. And and this isn't the
case across the board. I know that there
will be many engineers out there who do
the whole gamut like I described before,
but there are equally a lot of us who
ended up working in roles where we were
just coding. That's all we were expected
to do. which means that we haven't had
the opportunity to practice those other
skills as much that they are someone
else's job and those people have become
very good at those jobs.
So what happens now when AI is able to
do the bit that we've specialized in
rather well and a lot faster than most
humans can type then we need to start
looking a little bit broader at some of
those other areas that previously some
of us got to do in in that sense
learning how to elicit requirements.
That's probably a really good skill to
start looking for opportunities to to
practice and to learn. Is it quite as
enjoyable as reversing a linked list?
Maybe not to everyone. There will be
value in that. And architecting systems,
that's the technology career ladder or
the software engineering career ladder
seems to put an architect kind of at the
top of the food chain, right? Like you
you have to have gone through all the
hard yards before you get to be an
architect. It doesn't really make sense
to come out of university as a software
architect. You haven't felt the pain
yet. you have to have lived through
working out why that architecture just
doesn't make sense. So, how do you teach
those skills without having had that
background? Again, we're back to the
beginning of the conversation that it's
hard to even fathom how you're going to
learn those experiences, but at least
for anyone who's currently a software
engineer, start looking for
opportunities to think about the bigger
picture, the architecture, the system
design that fits best in this particular
use case. Wow. If you're going to start
looking at aentic systems, that's a
whole new area that there really aren't
that many specialists in yet because
it's such a new domain and systems where
you're actually using an LLM as the
orchestrator that decides for itself
which tool or skill to use next. How do
you even test that? Because now it's
non-deterministic and we're not very
good at thinking through
non-determinism. It's it's that
unpredictability is a bit unsettling.
So, yeah. And the more we go down that
that avenue, I think trust becomes a
massive deal particularly because when
we're thinking about agentic and taking
on greater tasks, it'll be interesting.
There's definitely a journey that we
need to go on here with trusting results
from
LLMs. It's amazing actually just in the
short time that that LLMs have or AI has
really been more mainstream in the last
couple of years. How much more or how
much less should I say trust and
security is talked about in general? I
remember it was a case of oh my gosh we
can't use this in our production
environments or we need to go through
the CISO first to work out whether we
can use this tool. These days it's oh my
god people are rushing to try and work
out how they can make those productivity
gains from whether it's from the board
from the top down the CEO down. But I
think as we get more autonomous with our
development, I guess what is the trust
dynamic in terms of us first of all
understanding whether the code is doing
the right thing, but secondly us
stepping away from that code. We can
only step away from that code if we
truly trust the AI that is that is
generating that. What do we really need
do you feel to actually truly trust this
process? Yeah. So the research that I've
seen on trust is emerging. I would say
that there was a lot more research or
there has been a lot more research
around the productivity gains which is
probably why as you say so many
companies are tripping over themselves
to to get in on that action but the the
trust
aspect what I've experienced it a bit
myself right these three just using
these tools but you you have the sense
that expectations are pretty high
because you've read about it your first
experience with it is pretty good so
you've got it's pretty pretty high
expectations, but then the
unpredictability of it starts to erode
that trust and it's hard to rebuild it.
Whereas with humans, you start off with
less trust, but you build it up over
time through
interactions. I remember doing a lot of
reading about this when I was trying to
be the best engineering manager that I
could be. How do you gain that trust
sufficient to be able to give people
constructive feedback? Because no one
really likes to hear constructive
feedback. People say that they want all
the feedback because it helps them grow
and that is absolutely true, but it can
hurt to hear something that that you've
not done well or that you could improve.
And so, how do you get better at giving
that type of feedback? The trick is you
need to build trust. You can't just give
feedback to someone who you have no
relationship with and expect that
they're going to take it on on the nose.
They're just going to accept your
feedback and you're a nobody to them.
But if you've taken the time to have I
think it's something like three positive
interactions with somebody then you're
more likely to have a positive
interaction about giving them some
feedback. So that's how humans build up
our trust with one another and hopefully
over time it increases and you learn to
finish each other's sentences and if
something happens to break that trust
you you then you can rebuild it through
a lot of effort. With AI, it feels a bit
different. Like you start off maybe
having a lot of trust in it and then you
hit a brick wall when it's going around
in circles and producing something
that's not at all what you asked for and
you're telling it that's not what you
asked for and it's agreeing with you
because it often it doesn't signal that
doubt. Right? That's one of the main
reasons why that trust erodess because
it's so confident in telling you the
wrong thing and then all you have to do
is ask it about it and then it changes
its mind completely and you're like no I
was just asking a question I didn't
expect you to go and undo the just stop
please that that trust is is really
important but how do we build it so
actually I read a very interesting paper
about something that Google researchers
are calling seamful AI eye. So, I'm not
sure I'd heard the word seamful before,
but if you think about most of the time
we're building seamless experiences,
right? We're trying to hide away the
seam so that you're not even aware of
it. But what this paper talks about is
maybe that's the wrong approach. Maybe
to in increase creativity and confidence
what we actually in using particularly
AI coding assistance and software
engineering maybe what we need to do is
actually highlight those scenes and use
them to our advantage. For example, one
of the use cases they suggest is in
those cases where the AI is not
confident, it should not pretend to be
confident and it should tell you here's
my opinion on how you could here's some
code that would solve the problem. But I
have a confident a confidence rating of
20%. And that could be an indicator to
the human in the loop, the developer to
go, ah, this is one of those situations
where I need to take over a bit more and
not just trust the AI. For boilerplate
stuff, it should have a confidence level
of much, much higher because it's just
boilerplate code. There's not too many
different ways to solve that problem. So
go for it. So maybe you can calibrate
that trust through these very
intentional subtle hints. Equally code
reviews then can really be focused on
the areas where it has least trust
rather than try and spend your time
equally across a code review. The areas
that are probably highest risk and also
lowest trust from the AI. So those are
the areas that that you we as humans can
work together with AI to to make it more
solid. Another paper that similar group
of authors had written about was that
they found upon interviewing software
engineers that creativity in software
engineering isn't necessarily what you
think it is. It's not all about
something totally novel. It's about
building up a novel way of stitching
together existing components and
libraries and frameworks. essentially
finding novel ways to reuse and put
together bigger systems from existing
components in terms of creativity then
in order to encourage creativity perhaps
in those more complex pieces of logic
that you're getting some help from an AI
coding assistant with from it if it has
multiple ways that it could solve that
problem some of which might be might
encourage reuse for example then it
could give you more than one option and
explain why in some cases is this would
be better for reusability and in these
cases you might prioritize these aspects
of it and really highlight that there
are many choices to be made here. The AI
is not going to make that decision for
you. You get to make that decision
because that's how you express your
creativity through that interaction.
Perhaps a bit more trust is built as
well. Yeah. Yeah. I like that. I would
trust if AI if LLMs gave me multiple
options and I chose the right one and I
could see its I don't want to say
thinking but I could see its process
that would fill me with more trust being
able to say actually yeah this is good
and I would actually feel more ownership
of that as well which is probably
another important thing. So I guess as
we think about the identity pendulum as
you mentioned charity majors refers to
it when we think about the potential
careers that could exist in this world
whereby we're changing identity I guess
do you still see the a software engineer
being being even a title? Do you feel
there are going to be diff various
flavors of software engineers? Let's get
the crystal ball out and try and think
of what what we think maybe software
engineers in the AI era, what the job
looks like. Yeah, I think we're going to
need to become very comfortable using
AI. So, I I think we probably take some
of us might take it for granted that
it's just like talking to another human
because actually there's a lot of
similarities between interacting if
you're prompting if you're chatting with
an AI. It really is like talking to
another human. And in fact, in my
research, what I've seen is when people
are asked like, "How would you improve
your prompt engineering skills?" The a
lot of answers are around improve your
communication skills. Lean into that.
It's a some people think of it as a more
formal means of communication. Some
think it's actually just like talking to
one of your colleagues and explaining to
them how you would like something done.
Maybe getting good at writing, maybe
getting good at teaching and leading in
that sense. in terms of yeah if that's
the role or a lot more of that role then
are you still a software engineer I
think the role will be around for a
while to come thankfully because like I
said earlier there's still so many
systems that need the skills that we
have today but learning how to use the
AI a variety of AIs as well because they
have their nuances right different
models even have their nuances the wind
surf and cursor are quite different to
something like GitHub copilot although
it's catching And then there's the
multimodal um AIs that you can use to
generate images and stuff. So getting
good at using a variety of these to
supercharge yourself. I think those are
skills that any individual really, not
just software engineers, but any
individual should get good at. And then
beyond that, I think honestly think
through the new problems that will be
created as a result of working in this
new way, right? is inevitably over time
we're going to be writing code faster
because that vigilance decrement that we
talked about the just produce more more
more and so we're we're absolutely going
to see as we're already starting to see
code take a different shape and perhaps
a little bit less stable. So maybe
focusing on the tooling that would help
identify those problems before they
happen. Highlight where you know imagine
being able to look into a software
solution from the outside in and go this
version that you're about to release to
production has more change in it than I
think you realize. Are you aware of the
fact that this business logic has now
changed? And maybe that's a new tool
that no one's built yet. So that could
become a whole domain that people start
focusing on that the test automation is
we have a vision of what test automation
looks like today but maybe if we start
considering these evals that's another
extension of it and there'll be tooling
around that so maybe you could become
more of an expert in that domain and so
there will be new specialtities that
people can go and focus on but I think
the critical thing there is
imagination I think that's probably a
skill that we don't talk about often
It's odd to call it a skill. Unless you
were hoping to become a children's book
writer or something and where
imagination is critical, but being able
to imagine something that that's
actually where it all starts. If you can
imagine something with these tools
today, you can probably build a version
of it. You need to imagine it. So, where
do you get that curiosity and that seed
of imagination from? Yeah. And very
often being too deep in the weeds
actually pulls us away from that. Yeah.
I really like the analogy that you
called before as well with the kind of
architect role that today people
actually do strive for and it's seen as
that progression from an engineer to an
architect and I think I personally see
that as a as a potential future for an
engineer where they will still be that
engineer but it'll be an architect's
role as an engineer. Yeah. Yeah. And I
was just going to say one more thing.
Much like during the industrial
revolution from what is written about
it, the those who were doing the job
manually, some of them moved into roles
where
they really understood the tools, the
machinery that could now do the job that
they used to do so that they could
wrangle them, just piece them together,
improve them, fix them when they broke.
So at their
core, LLMs are probably a special type
of work that not every software engineer
is going to become the data scientist,
AI specialist. However, that's like the
beating heart I reckon that's going to
drive a lot of other systems be it
because that's the LLM is the
orchestrator of an agentic system or
it's underlying a number of agents
within your IDE or something. So
understanding how those systems are
pieced together, the telemetry, the
observability, how do you wrangle a
system that is non-deterministic in
nature that has it at its core this
incredible
like computational brain that is making
its own decisions. Yeah. Become an
expert at running those systems which
are completely different to the systems
we run today. similar and that they're
probably still going to use a database
and they're probably still going to run
on a server somewhere. Those things
might remain the same, but the
orchestration of it will be quite
different. Learning to wrangle those
systems and fix them when they break and
be able to identify where the issue is,
that will become quite an interesting
job. I imagine maybe that's the
architect of the future as well. Yeah.
And history's shown us time and time
again how these kind of disruptive
changes creates these jobs. Exactly like
you just said. And I think that's
definitely the destination we need to
strive for. Annie, thank you so much. I
must encourage those who haven't read
your blog to absolutely take the time to
to read through that because I think it
was is beautifully written, but very
poignant to a lot of the challenges that
that we all face right now. So
definitely read that if you haven't had
the time or get AI to summarize it if
you want to be truly AI
embracing. Annie, thank you so much for
taking the time. It was an absolute
pleasure to chat with you. Thanks,
Simon. and I really enjoyed the chat.
Excellent. And for those of you
listening, please do tune in to the next
episode. And if you haven't already,
make sure you subscribe and like this
episode as well. Thanks and see you next
[Music]
time. Thanks for tuning in. Join us next
time on the AI Native Dev brought to you
by Tesla.